software engineering radio episode 83
future driven development with Jeff
DeLuca
[Music]
welcome listeners to yet another episode
of software engineering radio this is
episode 83 before we get to this week's
or well shouldn't say this week's before
we get to the content of this episode
which is Martin Lippert interviewing
Jeff DeLuca on future driven development
please don't forget you should go to the
website as a - radio dotnet click on the
link on the left which is to get
together and inform us about whether
you're going to come or not and well
under which circumstances we really need
to know this so we can go ahead and plan
or maybe also not plan if we don't see
enough interest okay have fun with this
episode and please welcome Martin okay
so welcome Jeff - to self engineering
radio and before we start I would like
to ask you if you could introduce
yourself to our listeners okay well
thank you thanks for inviting me to
speak my name is Jeff Toluca yeah I do a
lot of things in OIT but what I like to
do most is project management and that's
what I've been doing for a long time 15
20 years I'm the inventor of creative
effector driven development which is one
of the agile methodologies and that's
what I've been doing here in Hamburg ok
great thanks for being here so can you
tell us a bit more about what is
featured driven development I heard it
in the area of agile methodologies so
what what is it about well figure driven
development is really just the why I run
software projects and I've been doing
that for some period of time it was much
later the FDA was given a name and then
written about and in and then it was
after that that it was blessed if you
like by the founding fathers is one of
these ad kala methodologies so it's my
approach to running software projects it
predated agile but it's it's one of the
original founding agile methods so how
does a heard as feature driven
development look like it's a fairly
simple process it's has five or
methodology it has five processes in it
or five major steps it gives those pros
is written or described in only one or
two pages each and it tells you what to
do
so it's it's not you know six or seven
hundreds of pages of vagueness like rap
or rational unified process you know
it's not a xxx volume epic like method
one or some of these heavyweights sort
of things it's very practical it's
focused on since I'm a project manager
and that's what I do for a living it's
focused on the sorts of issues that we
have yeah
how do you do fixed price development
work how we answer questions such as how
far along are you how far is there left
to go and you know being able to do that
against the baseline with good coverage
and good accuracy okay so so how does it
look like in practice so I would like to
start a future driven development
project so what what what do I do
okay well the first step in fakie driven
development is we bring together what we
call domain experts which is ideally
real users or business people we bring
them together with our senior developers
and we do an activity called modeling
modeling the domain so the domain
experts will come in they describe their
domain their business in a series of
roughly 20 minute or so topics we'll do
question and answer while they're
describing this piece of their business
and then we'll break into teams and
collaboratively developers and business
people together will compose models in
support of those walkthroughs so in
terms of artifact production there's
this overall model that's produced but
really the secret ingredients if you
like the knowledge transfer that's
taking place it's a design activity but
it's also requirements analysis and
requirements discovery okay and and you
you said you you you create some kind of
model so those models look like they
they formalized or just non formalized
well they're formal in the sense that
they are genuine UML class diagram okay
but the way we actually do it is we use
pieces of flipchart paper we use color
post-it notes they're post-it notes
represent the classes we write the names
on them and stick them on sheets of
paper and working in a team low fidelity
like that and then each team will bring
their model up to the room and present
it to the other teams and there'll be a
question and answer on why there's
differences and we get differences of
perspective of the business differences
in interpretation and these things are
captured explicitly and
come to agreement on what the right
shape for this particular part of the
domain should be okay and you do this
kind of design sessions together with
the customer yeah absolutely
domain experts yeah so it sounds a bit
bit different than they now they have
agile methodologies where for example in
extreme programming you you know do not
talk about UML diagrams right you more
talk about user stories or feature
stories okay well yeah stories would be
more analogous to features which is the
next step in in FTAs so yeah you're
right every day is different to most of
the other agile methods in this one area
and so what we're talking about here is
that they're all iterative incremental
approaches as is FTD however if we're to
pure in our iterative approach meaning
that we're also going to iterate through
requirements itself then then it's hard
for us as a project manager to answer
the question how far along are you how
far is there left to go it's very hard
to answer their question and be accurate
when we haven't looked at all of the
requirements yet and so there needs to
be some sort of informational analytical
activity up front that will give us
enough knowledge to be able to set a
baseline with good coverage and good
accuracy so that we then can answer
these questions now it's it's not a big
design up front or a heavy activity I
mean we'll be doing this roughly one
week of time for every three months of
construction effort in a project so for
a six month project we'll be doing this
for about two weeks and we'll be coding
then in week 3 in an XP project Ron
Jeffries will be coding in week one and
as Jim Highsmith wrote in one of his
books you know so an FTD project if
talukas coding in week 3 Ron Jeffries is
coding in week 1 it's really not a
significant difference okay
I see well after the modeling is done we
go away and we build a features list and
a features list is simple functional
decomposition of the domain so we simply
break down the business into all of the
various steps that need to be done to
perform the functions they need we write
these features out in client language so
in client valued terms and we have a
particular naming template for that and
then we simply go along and design and
build feature by feature until we're
done so against features could then be
somewhat analogous to story
somewhat analogous to use cases but
fictive tend to be a little more
granular than no thing so they're more
fine-grained more fine-grained yeah okay
so what would be the next step you have
the feature list and now we have the
figures list I will set a plan and then
we simply iterate and we'll design and
build groups of figures at a time and
until we're completed ok and and how do
those those groups of features came into
the the project plan what we'll do at
runtime is so we've got this features
list we built initially when then we'll
set the plan for you know what sequence
we're going to build things in and now
at runtime we'll start plucking features
out of this list we have freedom in what
arrangement we want to do that but we're
guided by you know dependencies were
guided by what dates with a great
certain amounts of function should be
delivered and then the cliff programmers
will come along assemble those features
we put them into work packages which is
how we move a group of features through
design and build at a time they'll form
a picture team we'll do design which is
sequence diagramming in an object system
and then then we'll go away right the
recode that needs to be done inspect it
you know string test unit test it and
what gets promoted to build is a client
valued function so who is who's the
person that plans those those features
into into these work chunks and and for
the development sounds like like the
development team does it or does it the
customer no that's that's the two levels
of planning if you like so there's
upfront we get together with the
customer or modeler domain and use that
knowledge transfer to build a features
list to set our high-level plan and our
high-level plan simply says for fare
very fairly large chunks of features in
what calendar month will that amount of
work finish and that tends to follow the
major workflow will business cycle in
the area this comes out of the modeling
activity so when you ask a customer to
come in and describe their business in a
series of 20 minute or so topics those
topics that petitioning will tend to
follow the maker workflow or business
cycle in the domain you know so take
lending at banking for an example and we
start off with prospecting then we
create a basic application maybe just a
name and address and then we specify
what sort of loners are going to be a
credit card and more googling overdraft
next we specify what security will be
pledged to secure the line what
collateral then you do credit evaluation
you know you submit for approval and and
honor goes and so those would be the fit
those high-level chunks if you like and
we'll then a high-level planning time
will say you know what calendar month we
think those things will complete by so
we'll have a very coarse plan that goes
back to the client that says something
like you'll get prospecting in January
you know you'll get basic application in
March and you know individual lines of
credit in June and and and so on so
that's a high level planning if you want
to think of it that way just as the
modeling is high level design now when
we get construction time the engine if
you look at the project there's a
just-in-time detailed designs taking
place which is the sequence diagramming
and then there's custom time detailed
planning so when we decide that okay
we're going to do these ten features
let's say it's at that point in time
that a chief programmer and it's a chief
programmer that's doing this he will
Lester may write here's his dates for
those milestones across those ten
features and so then at that point in
time but it's at this work package level
and the work package can't take longer
than ten weeks so sorry ten days two
weeks so that's the fixed batch if you
like in FDD however it doesn't mean
though that there's a two-week iteration
in FTD so it's not a fixed two-week
cycle there'll be multiple work packages
active at any point in time and they'll
be overlapping different stages of their
own life cycles so there isn't a fixed
two-week iteration if you like in FTD
but we never do a batch of work that
takes longer than two weeks
okay so you do not have these these kind
of or fixed iterations where you staff
the iteration with those different
features and stuff like they're that are
all finished at the end of the iteration
so you have more these these work shanks
and they are planned over time instead
of fixed iterations fixed time you have
more and more this kind of time boxing
per feature and not time boxing in
general well yeah I mean time boxing is
a different philosophy so time box
management says that the date is the
only thing that matters and in order to
make a date will drop function or drop
features so that that's not what we do
here what we're doing here is we're
saying that when we backup
group of features for design and build
into one of these work packages so that
they don't get too big I want to
constrain that effort to no more than
two weeks worth of effort but if we
don't complete then it's going to turn
red and it'll stay red until it's
finished I won't drop the features out
just to arbitrarily make some day so
it's different in that respect it's
different that it's not a fixed two-week
iteration in that it isn't a fixed
two-week iteration across the entire
project so each group of features and I
can't take longer than two weeks to
complete but there'll be multiple of
these work packages active at any point
in time and they could be at different
stages of their own two-week cycles so
that's that's the difference there if
you like okay so where the feature list
we've planned in work chunks and what it
was the next step that is described in
future two development was I once we
once we then start actually designing
and building the features in these work
packages that's essentially it we're
going to keep doing that until all of
the figures we identified in the
fishiest lister done at which stage the
system is complete we've we've now
designed and built all of the functional
requirements okay in in many agile
methodologies is the eighth year of
continuous integration and then daily
deploy minami or whatever really is
often really early does it look like in
future driven develop yeah that's
fundamental to every day so it's
absolutely continuously integrated the
only incremental to build in FTD is
itself a client valued function right
and since the figures are so very
granular I mean features are being
completed every week and completely is a
great word to get to use in a project by
the way and we get to use that word a
lot in FTD okay so yeah every feature
that is promoted to build is itself a
client valued function it could you know
it could be broken off and tested
independently in client valued terms and
so that does allow a lot of parallelism
for system tests for example and so
inherently then every feature is itself
a continuous integration the builds are
inherently deployable at any point in
time so we are continuously integrating
if theta is heavily incremental you know
and incrementalism is the antidote to
integration hell yeah I give it a system
to production after every every week or
every work Chang that is complete well
that's possible yeah
something I would probably do all right
I mean trying to deployed it to
production weekly would be interesting
but it's certainly possible yes each of
those builds is essentially deployable
system what you can do though is you can
hand off the system test at that sort of
frequency so we can get a lot more
parallelism but yeah I would
me personally I wouldn't recommend we
try and deploy the production that often
but yeah if it works you could yeah
before it would be possible
I remember came back came back writing
in this book about daily deployments
yeah could be possible for web
applications maybe well yeah again no it
does he really mean daily deploy to
production I'm not sure I would do that
but but yeah it's possible if they would
handle that yeah absolutely it would
absolutely handle that it's it's unit of
development the future is very granular
and so that gives you a lot of the
flexibility to do this sort of thing and
you do some some some kind of replanting
continuously or well I'd say the detail
planning in the detail design is all
done just in time so we'll only
estimator feature at the moment we
actually now have to design and build it
mm-hmm so in that respect you could say
yeah that's been continuously very
valuated because we're only having to
make those estimates at the point we
actually do the work so that mean also
that you leave these initial design
initial planning the rough rough plan
for whatever a year or I don't know is
is adapted on time as well what could be
but I think the the secret to their
success is that that initial plan is is
very course though right it's very large
blocks of function and we only
designating which whole calendar month
we're going to deliver it you know we'll
say you'll get this function in February
we don't say February one off every 28
we just say February and so we get a lot
of play now in the detailed sequencing
of this stuff and so it's it can happen
but it's not a majority case that we all
need to go back to those initial dates
and and revise them okay but you can
easily add stuff sure you can and if we
miss one of those dates one of those
things is going to go red I mean we have
a car to communication so one of those
boxes will go red but my this is a
philosophy but my bias here is it I
won't now later I won't try and turn
that thing back to blue which means in
progress or white not started just to
try and make the plan look good I mean
if it's late it's late and if that box
will stay red for a period of time
I think that's the important way to yeah
build up trust with the client it's a
very open and transparent system every
day and yeah so if something's late for
some reason we will have discussed that
and if it's okay it's okay but I'll
leave that box read until it finishes I
think it's it's very interesting to you
more about this transparency in future
development so what what are the
mechanisms and make the process
transparent only these these let's say
weekly deployment possibilities or are
there other techniques there's a lot of
techniques it's but it's the sort of
thing there's not well-suited to radio
so it's very visual so yeah there's a
lot of reports and tracking in FTD
there's a thing called a parking lot
cart which is very very popular now a
lot of other methods are using it non
outgoing methods as well this sort of
rolls up those large accounts of
function it's a it's a chart that it's
got like colored boxes for what each of
the things are it's all expressed in
client language it's a decomposition of
the business itself and there's a color
system for you know why does not started
they go blue if they're in progress
these little progress bars that show the
progress movement they go red if they're
late they go green if they complete and
so that's a very visual way of
communicating value back to the client
just everything on their chart is you
know some grouping of business function
underneath that then there's a lot of
detailed reporting of you know the
individual faces themselves all of their
discrete milestones s they built and
deployed and if any one fiction misses
one of its milestones we capture recent
takes for why that is and who was
working on it and all of this stuff is
there and visible if people want to dive
into that level of detail okay but it is
a little hard to describe you sort of
need to see it yeah but there are there
are samples of all of this stuff at the
FDA website okay so we can we can put
the box around and the show notes yeah
so we get this rough over you but about
the the planning and the release cycles
and stuff like that so can you tell us
more about the details inside the
development cycle so I remember extreme
programming giving you a lot of advice
how to actually implement feature with
test-driven development and pepper
cramming and stuff like that okay are
there there's similar techniques there
are certain techniques we recommend to
use but we done without
do a lot of how-to at that sort of level
right so if didi says for example when
you come to detail design let's assume
an object system the primary artifact
we're going to produce in the detail
design is the sequence diagram so that's
now looking at the classes in this model
how are they going to collaborate to
perform this function and as we work
that out we are now going to populate
that model with content we're going to
add methods and attributes to the
classes to be able to perform this
function so if T talks about doing that
as a practice there are other things
like writing you know your class and
Method prologue first and considering
error flows at design time rather than
later
those sorts of things it's also says
that we should do formal design and code
inspections as a technique but if they
doesn't say anything about how to run
one so like a lot of agile methods which
is one one of the many things there Joel
gets right all of the methods is that
you know they recognize that software
constructions of human activity and you
we can't be prescriptive about what you
do in every possible circumstance I mean
projects are just far too complex
we can't prescribe for every given
situation what do you do yeah right it
says you should do inspections it
doesn't tell you how to run one it
assumes you cliff programmers know how
to do that or the if they don't they
know to ask for help and if they're not
smart enough to know either of those two
things then no method is really going to
help you yeah at the term chief
programmer yeah think for a second third
time now okay what is the wrong name and
that's showing my heritage a little bit
but it's just a role now so it's you're
a class developer if your development
leads or your senior developers or you
know whatever label you want to use it's
the the good ones right the guys that
have that design and code ability have
that sort of full lifecycle experience
so it's it's not a formal role in in ftt
projects I guess it depends how you
define formal I mean we we need to
recognize right I mean variations in
programmer productivity one of the most
well measured and experimented and
understood parts of IT we know that the
good ones are anywhere from 10 to 50
times they're not so good ones and so if
we're going to run software projects I
mean we must be
that sort of stuff just as we need to
worry about differences in complexity
from one class to another we need to be
aware of differences in skill levels
from one resource to another so if they
certainly understands and embraces their
and so it says those developers the
better ones they're the ones that I want
to be involved in the modeling they're
the ones that I want to lead the design
but I want them to actively mentor the
other developers with as many and
frequent interactions as possible so I
want to transfer some of their ten to
50x productivity as quickly as I can and
so there if you like sort of that the
control point if you like they're the
ones that are going to facilitate that
detailed design they're the ones that
will make sure the things drink tests
and unit tests before we promote it in
to build those sorts of activities okay
but there are no no explicit activities
so that well and the chief programmer is
allowed to do that it's more than use
you stuff those people together into
into the project I mean they're the ones
that decide you know whether we're going
to inspect or not they that's their
judgment call they're the ones that go
along and report the dates yeah but
there's no reason that another developer
couldn't do that it just makes sense for
the chief programs to do it since
they're the ones orchestrating the work
okay so that's really all it is it's not
a ceremonial position if you like
there's no hire ceremony with the thing
but that it is a recognition of there
are different skill levels with
developers and so we want the better
ones to be in control of some of these
things and mentoring they're not the
less better ones
for what what kind of projects do you
think future driven development is is
the best method in contrast to many
maybe other agile methodologies or other
processes that's an interesting question
when if I I don't think about things
they're wise so you know so firstly we
FDA is the best method I don't have that
sort of philosophy yeah you know I don't
consider FDA the one and only one true
way that software development can be
done yeah
and when I work with people the first
thing I tell them is you know if you've
got something that's already working for
you then my advice is going to be to
keep using it right whatever that may be
yeah and if it's reliable and repeatable
and hope I don't you tell us how you do
that so you know it's it's not often a
you can't I don't believe you could be
purist about this starfire
not often I'll do a hundred percent of
sitting implementation I'll look at what
are the current resources what are the
current practices what are the
constraints what's working and what's
not and then it you know it's a mix and
match of practices and approaches so I
certainly have my opinions on what
things I believe in and that work and
things that I wouldn't do given a free
choice like I'm not a fan of use cases
as an example but if you're using key
use cases and they're working for you
then I'm going to be using them too if
we're working together yeah there was a
lending system built for a bank in
Singapore which is sort of the poster
project for FTD now I don't like use
cases but that project had three and a
half thousand pages of them okay so yeah
well absolutely work with them if
they're working for you so in terms of
FTD being the best that I think of it
that way the other part of your question
is what sort of project is it suitable
for again I have a different view here I
don't see the agile methods the lining
that way I think it's more about people
than it is about the methods you know I
think certain methods resonate with
certain people and they're the ones they
should explore so what I tell people
when they ask is this sort of question
you know which method should I use
Jim Highsmith is one of the fathers of
the agile movement he's written several
great books one of them is called agile
software development ecosystem okay we
can put that in show notes as well again
okay now in that book he describes all
of the six or seven agile methods in the
one book so you can buy that book you
read it now you know two or three of
those methods are going to resonate with
you they're going to call out your name
and and two or three the others are not
going to resonate with you and so
whatever those two or three are they're
the ones you should probably explore
yeah
and whether that's if they do or not you
know to me it really isn't isn't much
import the only caveat I would or a
warning I would put in here is you know
so you might read this book and you find
a method that resonates strongly with
you but it might not resonate strongly
with your company so there is the you do
have the problem of having to sell it
all so are there any any any special
requirements for for the company that
the company should fulfill to be able to
do feature development well there are
certain cultural things and I think
that's if today specific I think that's
common to all agile methods I mean agile
makes it all understand software
chuckling human activity and it makes
those sorts of concerns first class
issues you know so there are certain
cultures where that's going to be
challenging like you know they're I
don't wanna name them but there are
certain cultures we're saying now is
just not the done thing you know well
that's very unnatural would be very
difficult to implement any HR method in
an in an environment like that yeah you
know they're all pretty open and
transparent methods and we need to be
able to reset plans or you know say no
or say things that haven't worked and so
they're the sorts of cultural issues
that are in play okay we heard a bit
about about the customer collaboration
and it seems like the customer
collaboration happens mostly in the
first part of this rough design stuff is
there any customer collaboration any
unknowing customer collaboration yeah
its continual so I mean we certainly do
this upfront activity and that's
full-time with them and and and that's a
nice way to bring us all together
actually but then it's continual after
that so as we're moving through in
building the features list we may need
to check back with the domain experts
that's not uncommon and then as we go
through and design and build features
often we need to check back with the
main experts again as well there'll be
things you know the high level staff has
a fairly high level when you get down to
the detail level there there tend to be
typical triggers where we'll need to
kick back with the domain either in the
form of a document or a person and
sometimes both so at the level of an
individual feature which is very tiny
very granular though those typical
triggers are algorithmic complexity or
data complexity so let me give you an
example of if either when we're doing a
shape modeling up front let's say it's a
lending system in a bank alright so
loans have many terms and conditions one
of the terms and conditions of a loan is
its interest rate now there's a simple
way to calculate interest and then
there's the way banks do it yeah and
then the tank is often and it's
negotiable for commercials and
corporates so if we were color modeling
for example we would have a blue term
and condition description class it's got
some sort of interest rate method on it
now in terms of the shape model at a
high level state that's enough we know
that shape is right when well now during
construction when we hit a c2 that has
to actually
calculate interest now I need to know
what that formula is what's the business
rule for doing this and in that
particular case I would probably be
kicking back with the domain most likely
in the form of a person and a document
yeah another example of this might be
data complexity if it's a commercial
mortgage say a hospital or a hotel you
know there's a lot of data elements a
lot of attributes need to be recorded
you know how many rooms does this thing
have how many beds per room which rooms
to have a spa bath this sort of thing
again when we shape modeling we don't
need to know all those hundred
attributes when we hit a fixture to do
with establishing a commercial security
commitment now I need now I do need to
know what those hundred attributes are
now I would probably click back with the
domain in the form of a document in that
case so there's two examples of where
we're going back to them in terms of
write more requirements analysis
there'll be just as many if not more
example so if you know going back to
them for clarification and and detail
that sort of thing and remember also
we're continuously delivering here so
there's a lot of feedback loop going on
also okay so this seems it seems like a
cultural issue for companies as well so
I have this this close collaboration
between customers and development teams
oh yeah and it's fundamental isn't I
mean this is one thing we get wrong and
I tell you a lot I mean yeah we know we
need good access to users and yet we go
to the business and ask for them and
they tend to always say they're too busy
oh yeah and but what do we do well we
default well we shouldn't it really
matters that's why I charles is you know
not only should you have good access to
them you should be co-located if you can
be yeah but we go to the business and we
ask for access to the users and they say
they're too busy and then we go ok and
we go off and try and build something
anyway well it's pretty hard to like a
group of people if we don't have access
to them yeah so you know yeah we need to
get much better at that we need to be
more assertive about this sort of stuff
I believe one of the primary tasks as a
project manager is education and it's to
educate those above you which senior
management in this particular case and
those below you the people working for
you and in terms of educating those
above us save the business
yeah we need to be we need to get a lot
better at that and making them
understand the implications of these
sorts of things you want us to build our
IT systems that
Liuzza's but we can't get access to them
because they're too busy
how does feature driven development
relates to other HR methods earlier
where is you know I tend to come at it
more from the people so you know you'll
find a method resonates with you that's
when you sit explore and if it doesn't
then you probably shouldn't you know at
the detail level there are some
differences of course I mean there were
two places where FTA in XP disagree and
that is pair programming and collective
ownership but if you look at the other
10 practices in XP if they'd a dozen as
most project should so I think what's
more interesting so rather than the
detail differences I think what's more
interesting is what skin comment what
binds them together and that's one of
the real gifts I think of the agile
community its those four value
statements that's what binds all of the
six or seven methods together and at the
detail level yeah there are some
differences but they all share that
common value system you know we value a
working code more than any other form of
progress and you know those those value
statements so to me that's the more the
more interesting part Steve Hays is I
believe the best Experian
you know we believe if you call yourself
an edge list or part of that agile
community but you want to hug you with
the detail level about the Sdn versus
from versus whatever then you don't get
agile I mean if you really want to argue
with that level of detail you don't get
agile it's the common value statements
that bind all those methods together so
you could easily think of of projects
doing some parts of future doing
development combining them with other
parts of scrum absolutely and that
that's a common mix scrum and if today
is a fairly common I think scrum and
everything is a fairly common make cycle
a scrums very popular these days ken
does a terrific job promoting that but
yes Grumman XP is the dominant
combinations Grumman if there is very
common also so how does this combination
often looks like well what is your
experience on this this scrum and future
driven development combination I don't
have a lot of detail on the scrum side
obviously I mean if I'm running the
project it's gonna be pretty much 50
days so you know so but I you know I
know scrum talks about more from a
management perspective and so
it's fairly easy to slide underneath it
right more discreet tasks and techniques
which is what's in a lot of if they do
mm-hmm because also yxp can fit with it
fairly well okay
so I have have this kind of off scrum
features for for for the management and
future development for for for the
actual implementation yeah you can do
that I mean there'll be points of
difference I mean there's a burn down
card Instagram but that's very similar
to the trend reporting FTD I mean one
plots up one plots down but they're
reasonably similar other big differences
would be if you're using scrum as an
overriding management philosophy I mean
it does have a fixed iteration the time
box which is the scrub itself so you'd
be a superimposing that over the top of
50 but that would be easy to do again
granular features gives you all sorts of
flexibility in how you want to package
the worker you know scrum does daily
stand-ups I've done daily stand-ups on a
lot of projects but I'm mandated there's
a practice but there's a lot of
similarity and good feeling here I mean
Ken's a good project manager you know
and I like scrum I have no problem
recommending it okay so I have to ask
the the typical agile methods question
what happens to fixed price projects so
any of these kind of the features are
flexible and we could replan stuff like
that and any of the old-fashioned
fashioned self engineering guys say okay
now I have a fixed price project and
this is contract negotiation stuff and
yeah how does it look like for future
driven development well every project
I've ever run has been fixed price so I
mean that's the majority case oh yeah so
I think time and materials work is
really the minority case and I mean I
never get asked to do it so if people
are able to pick up work like that and
then you know they're better at the
marketing side of this than I am
so so now a fixed-price development is
the norm it's what I've been doing for
you know 15 20 years and and so
therefore obviously FDA is optimized
around there and so it uses this upfront
activity as a way to calibrate what that
construction estimate ought to be but
because the plan is course right I've
got a lot of flexibility in the detailed
sequencing of all of those features as
long as I still hit these fairly broad
milestones though mm-hmm yeah at fixed
price a fixed price development is the
norm it fits very well okay and for
contract negotiation situations too
between these contribution situations
you have to to to write down the
features or the main stuff that this
office should fulfill yeah okay well it
I mean it's a path to this so the really
interesting part of contract negotiation
is actually non-functional requirements
that's the more challenging part once
you've built a features list right
they're very granular every feature
entity is expressed in client valued
language and it's a complete
decomposition of all the functional
requirements so that now becomes a clear
statement of work for the functional
requirements it's the non-functional
that I think are more challenging yeah
what I do there is non-functional
requirements really Eric a statement of
work issue yeah so they're things like
you know it must be usable or it must
perform well yeah and so the sort of
conversation you need to have with the
client then and it is really an
education process and we're also testing
the waters it's if you want to think of
it this way it's like a reverse
interview I'm interviewing them yeah so
if they demand something like it must
perform well okay well how are we gonna
measure that what does the form well
mean how do we measure it usually they
will stamp them but if it doesn't they
might come back and say okay must have
sub to second into in response time yeah
okay okay great well look you know we're
friend ending some existing systems you
already have so if you can instrument
this entire thing so you can isolate the
backend systems the network latency
between 18 hours as a server the other
workload that's going on the server the
virtual machine as well we're running in
the render time then out to the browser
and different levels of I even have very
different render times for tables and so
forth if you can instrument all of that
and isolate all of it out yeah I'll
guarantee you a sub to second code path
through our business logic you bet
now the point of having that
conversation is of course no one can do
their and so what we're looking for here
is reasonableness do they understand
what this really means so I'm looking
for reasonable is do it you know can we
look each other in the eye and what can
we write down here that makes both of us
feel reasonably safe but can't be
completely open-ended because these
non-functional is the the real
difficulty is in yeah what criteria
we're going to use to measure that stuff
well if you can't give criteria for how
it's going to be measured then how can I
possibly satisfy it
so when I'm having this conversation
though you know it really isn't contract
negotiation I'm looking to see do they
understand do they get the problem and
if I think they do and they're
reasonable yeah well let's work together
if I say that no they really don't
they're gonna be difficulty become busy
but at the end feature development is
built like many other agile methods on
this kind of customer collaboration
trust between the parties exactly right
yes to go to the lawyer
it may be your project have had anyway
so exactly but we can you know we can
upfront some of this activity by signal
functionals by having some of these
conversations up front we're gonna get a
feel for what's the relationship can it
be like between these two parties
because it yeah it doesn't need to be
collaborative
okay yeah are there any other things
about future dune development you would
like to to tell to our listeners any any
other things we we we missed till now
well not really I mean we hinted it most
of it I mean the things that draw most
people towards FTD is it gives them a
good baseline for reporting against and
that matters to a lot of commercial and
corporate in-house development and they
they really like it's tracking and
reporting so I mean if you go to the
website and look at the samples the
parking lot chart the trend report the
progress summary reports it's it's very
visual it's very transparent it's all
communicated in business terms and
that's what most people seem to really
like about it and it seems to be what
draws most people towards it there's
this awesome some documentation about
future development online well yeah
again if they go to that feature driven
development website that's where most of
the discussion sort of takes place I
mean it's not a high traffic well I
should say it's a very high reader right
traffic website doesn't have a lot of
new threads maybe one a week or
something like that I mean I don't do
anything in terms of marketing or
advocacy I mean I like to run projects
it's what I like to do but the threads
that are there are very high quality and
yeah if you browse that site and I've
linked the most interesting threads on
the home page then yeah that's where you
can learn a lot there's like a gallery
there with sample file there's photos
from projects and actual samples of
reports and and things like that okay
great so any any other pearls of wisdom
you will you would like to tell us just
remember that software construction is a
human activity and we really need unless
we can learn to think many can do
with human systems we really have no
hope with these software systems and I
guess the other thing I would say is we
also need the app much better at
educating those above us the business or
top management the implications are some
of the things they force us to do okay
great so thank you very very much for
for the interview and hope to see you
soon okay thank you for the invitation
Thanks
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website
so other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Cowley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details
you
[Music]